one of the most common misunderstandings
in the field of human performance
strengthing auditioning in muscle is the
relationship between muscle mass and
strength now we've covered the back end
on a separate video which is what
happens to strength when you add muscle
mass but I think the more interesting
question is the opposite right can you
get stronger without getting bigger
in other words adding more muscle mass
now this is important for people that
are in weight clay weight base class
sports like a wrestler or a boxer or
even an Olympic weightlifter or a power
lifter right so they have to continue to
get stronger but they can't afford to
add muscle mass or other people for a
thousand other reasons that don't want
to add muscle but they want to continue
to get stronger well anyone who has any
education in his field is gonna tell you
the answer is of course yes I mean just
look at the evidence
so we continually see people break
powerlifting and weightlifting records
which means they're getting stronger and
stronger and more effective in their
sport but they're not changing weight
classes but what's more important though
and what we're really going to dive into
in this installment of 55 minute
physiology is how that actually happens
physiologically alright because we know
the answer is yes so what we really want
to know is how do I program such that I
get the strength and power increases
without adding muscle size and then
what's the physiology behind that and of
course I'm always such a proponent of
science or I fundamentally believe if
you understand the physiology behind it
understanding why the programming does
what it does
becomes unbelievably obvious so let's
dive into it but before we do that I
want to take a quick second to remind
you this entire website and all these
videos I do for free all right it's out
there I fundamentally believe everyone
should have a chance to know this
information I think we're past the day
of charging for basic information like
this and more importantly I realize how
fortunate I am I grew up in a country
and I'm in a place and I have a job that
pays me well above what I need to
survive but not everyone is in that
situation and so I make these videos so
that all of you no matter where you are
in the world or socioeconomically can
I've access to good quality health
fitness performance nutrition
information having said that there are a
ton of costs associated with this I
actually am working on some things
behind the scenes where I
to get some of these transcribed and
just shorter quicker blog so you can get
the information that you're interested
in faster some questions that you can
use because I know a lot of you are
actually using this for your academic or
even high school classes and so I want
to add more depth to this and then that
just takes some cost because these
things take me a tremendous amount of
time so if you're enjoying these are
using these videos I would I would I
would hope I'm asking for you to go over
to my patreon page and that's Annie
Galvin
I'm sorry that's wwwp tree on Comm tour
/ Danny Galvin and just contribute a
buck or two so that website works such
that you can you know set a maximum
number of dollars that you can afford
say two bucks three bucks a month and
then you only donate based on when I
deliver content so you're not paying an
annual subscription for your anything
like that but if I post a new video you
get charged that dollar two or you can
just set a monthly donation or just make
a single donation every single penny
that goes into that patreon account goes
back to one of these people that I pay
to help me with this sign so I don't
take any of it as personal salary at all
the more money we can generate on the
backend the more I can set up this
infrastructure and so I could fire out a
lot of these videos a lot more often my
goal actually next year is to have a lot
more of these videos up and answer user
questions so once again if you can take
that quick second to pop over to that
account patreon patr
yo n com4 slash Danny Galpin and help us
contribute to spreading the word of
science and health and performance human
performance and nutrition I would
appreciate it alright so now for that
let's get back into it well any time I
you want to answer a programming
question or really any question I think
we should turn to the experts so in this
particular case who are the best in the
world about getting stronger but not
adding too much muscle mass and again
we're thinking muscle mass because we're
worried about people who either from you
know aesthetic reasons or for any other
reason don't want to add muscle or don't
want to add weight period to the scale
so the best the world this clearly in
general are the power lifters and
Olympic weightlifters and probably if
we're being technical we'd have to head
towards powerlifting because that sport
is truly the test of strength where of
course way the thing is more of a test
of power right and so we want to look at
these individual
here's a good example this is my friend
Stephie Coen a shot at dr. Stephie Coen
now she's one of the strongest women in
history of the world she's got about
twenty World Records or something like
that I'm sorry if I mess it up I know
it's a ton she weighs competes at 123
pounds and he's getting close to the
lifting four and a half times her body
weight which is an insane amount held by
the time you watch this he's probably
dead living 600 pounds at 125 pounds so
she continually throughout her career
has gotten have gotten has gotten
stronger and stronger and stronger but
she's still been able to sail in the way
same weight class and so we want to look
towards this community and say hey what
are the types of the programming things
they tend do and do and have in and
recommend that allow you to get stronger
faster or more powerful without getting
bigger well the first answer is what we
in the scientific community called the
said principle that's that acronym
stands for specific adaptation to
imposed a man what that means if you
want to get better at shooting
free-throws the best thing you could
ever do is shoot free-throws so if you
want to get better at picking something
up that you can't currently pick up or
pushing something or pulling something
or dragging something or whatever it is
you're trying to do the most specific
thing you could ever do to address that
programming lies would be to pick
something up that you can barely pick up
or can't quite pick up right and so in
other words very very very heavy things
so the adaptation is very specific to
the demand so if you look at two
individuals that are doing two different
types of workouts what you can see is
imagine one of the girls here on the
left and then the girl on the right say
they're doing different workouts but
they're both working equally hard
sleeping the same eating the same well
they would see different physiological
adaptations because of the way the
specific adaptation or the the demand
being placed on the body at the time
right so this programming stuff is
important in terms of how heavy you
should lift if you look at the bottom of
the figure here this is relative percent
again think this is what we call
intensity but think of this is how heavy
what percentage of on one right max well
for general strength train we're talking
about is something in this 80 plus
percent range now obviously we need to
change this based upon your background
okay this is just a general guideline
but the closer we can head to ourselves
to that 100 the better two other
important notes here unless you have
extends
of training and I mean 10 probably or
more years to me heavy strength training
you can't just do 100% every single day
especially the same movement you're
going to break so just think of this is
concept trying to get to this heavy
stuff as often as you can but still use
periodization still use appropriate
program design monitoring a volume and
all that stuff right we just want to
shift our self more towards that
strength as much as we can
point number two that's not a bad low
quality graphic or that's not me being
sloppy I'm not sloppy in my powerpoints
but do you notice how the hot another
strength actually goes past the 100 well
we'll talk about in a second there's
some several different ways when you can
actually lift something that's
quote-unquote greater than 100% of your
why not max
things like heaviiy Centrex or maybe
using some assistance can be helpful so
generally anything and in that that's
kind of heavy pretty heavy issue Ange if
you're a beginner more like say five
years left of heavy live or less of
heavy lifting or maybe even none you
don't need this start at 70 or 80 or
sorry 80 plus percent probably for
strength even as little as sixty percent
can be fine right so really imagine the
scale is kind of sliding back and forth
but mostly once you're fairly trained
98% a lot of time is what we're looking
for so because we're trying to lift at a
very very high load the number of
repetitions per set has to be small
right probably less than five or six
total again there's always a great hairy
there's no there's no hard and fast
lines it's not like it's six reps you
get strength and seven you get nothing
or 81 percent of strength and 79 percent
it's not strength it's not that specific
but just think we're trying to lift
something very very heavy so because
that we can only lift it a few times so
strength is down in that 1 to 6 ratio in
terms of order now generally we want to
do strength at the very beginning and
this goes back to basic program design
principles do what's most important
first in this case if the thing that's
most important to you is building
strength and you're going to do other
stuff say hypertrophy work or speed work
or conditioning work well conditioning
especially needs to be done after the
strength workout now there's plenty of
other exceptions in other videos one I
can explain to you when is
okay to do conditioning first but in
this particular instance if strength is
the primary goal there are two main
reasons why we want to do that before we
would do any of our conditioning work
number one if we're trying to do
strength at the same time we're doing
conditioning so imagine doing intervals
or doing a circuit or something like
that or trying to do conditioning before
we do our strength training well the
primary problem with that is you're
going to be tired if you're tired you
can't lift something maximally heavy now
that should make intuitive sense I if I
ask you to pick something up that it's
the heaviest thing you could ever
possibly pick up well I can almost
guarantee you with very few exceptions
you can't do that if you're tired that
percentage that maximal force you can
produce is going to slide down by two
three four ten fifteen percent some
number but whatever that number is if
that number is a half a percent well
that means you're half percent lower and
that's not a hundred so we need you to
be at at a very high force production
for strength training so conditioning is
going to compromise our ability to do
things at a high velocity or high force
more specifically which compromise that
of adaptation because now we're doing
something kind of tiring out of kind of
high force production and that's not
specificity number two in some cases if
you do a bunch of conditioning work
before your strength stuff you're now
going to take your smaller muscle groups
or even any of your larger muscle groups
but a fatigue muscle group and you're
gonna ask ask it sorry to produce force
and probably a compromising position
under tremendous load that my phone my
friends is just a recipe for potential
risk right a recipe for injury so I'm
not saying you can't ever certainly you
can especially as you become more
advanced athlete but for the most part
we want to be very cautious I'm not
gonna say never but just cautious of how
often we're gonna do our conditioning
before our strength work win the gold is
strength right there's just really a few
reason to do that stuff if the gold is
strength okay in terms of the movement
now when you go to the gym this is
another one of those fundamental
questions now people talk about what are
you doing the new today gym today
and a lot of people like to do what we
would call body part splits so Mondays I
do back and
biceps Tuesdays or triceps Wednesdays or
deltoids or things like this right
you've heard I'm sure you probably done
all right I know I have tons done at
tons of times well that would be
selecting the exercise that you're going
to do for the day based on the muscle
group see that in the bottom and green
sport coaches strengthening missionary
coaches generally tend to choose
exercises not by the individual muscle
group but by the movement pattern right
so are we trying to do a hinging
movement or we're doing a pressing
movement or doing a pulling movement or
we're doing a rotating movement well
both forms of exercise selection are
very are valid but it depends on the
goal you're trying to get at so in this
particular case when strength is the
goal while trying to maintain or
minimize muscle growth we generally want
to pick by the movement right we don't
need to do isolated individual muscle
work unless we've got a very specific
physical therapy reason or an asymmetry
or something for just you're not only
trying to get strong we select the
exercises based on the movement patterns
and then what we do is make sure we have
a reasonable balance throughout the day
and mostly through at least throughout
the week across all of our joints across
all of our ranges of motion in those
joints if you do that you're gonna be
able to do strength training fairly
frequently for a long time and not
induce any asymmetry or overuse injuries
because you're balancing the movement
patterns and that's what's most
important for this area all right so a
little more detail here you can use a
different system I would encourage you
honestly to generate your own system I
know a lot of other coaches that you
have a slightly different one but I do I
did want to give you a an overview or
some concepts of what some of these
movement patterns might be so for the
legs I like to think about it as being
three their squatting or pressing
hinging this would be like a deadlift or
an RDO or pulling some people call that
a lower body pull alright so I'll often
refer to if I was doing deadlifts today
I'll say I did a bunch of pulling today
pulling from the floor or I like a clean
pull or a snatch pull anything like that
is still a lower body movement but it's
a hinge hip hinging movement versus a
squat movement and then the third ones
lunge some people like to call these
single leg and some people will split up
lunging versus single leg because a
lunge is technically not a single leg
split squat those are slightly different
exercises but those are the general
categories of leg movements in terms of
the upper body you know we've got four
it's horizontal
pressing and pulling and then vertical
pressing and pulling and there's not a
lot of other distinction behind those in
terms of the core there is a course
flexion and extension there's rotation
and there's lateral flexion some people
like to call this six categories because
they'll say there's an anti component I
kind of lump those in so I don't care
what you like to do just in your head
make sure that if you're doing a lot of
flexion work say like a crunchy well
make sure you're also doing some what's
called an anti flexion which is avoiding
flexion so you don't want to flex when
you don't wanna flex anti extension work
right so doing extension work here where
you're actively going backwards well the
core needs to be able to avoid on one
extension so some people call that anti
extension or anti lateral flexion right
so imagine doing like a single arm
dumbbell and dumbbells pulling you down
well in this case you're using your core
muscles to nocked lateral flex anti
flexion versus actively flexing and
pulling up right all three important
ones this other stuff can get a bit
tricky and so the other ones I called
two kind of total body movements like
snatching it's a press it's a pull its
overhead press it's an anti overhead
anti flexion it's all kinds of other
stuff throwing jumping sprinting
rotating and pressing landmines complex
movements they don't necessarily fit in
that category right so again what we're
just trying to highlight don't think
detail here think concept what we're
trying to do is select our strength
exercises such that the movement
patterns that are typical of the human
body are roughly equally balanced
throughout our program right we just
don't want to go long stretches where
it's like hey I haven't done any
horizontal rowing this is why my
shoulders gotten gunky in the last five
weeks weird or you look at your program
and realize boy I'm doing a lot of lower
body hinging but I'm not doing any lower
body pressing no lower by squatting or
it's all single it's all bipedal a
bilateral work two legs I haven't done
any single leg work or whatever the case
is and you don't again you don't need to
have a one-to-one math you don't have to
have X equal exactly equal ratios within
all these movement pattern
just a reasonable pattern across the
week across the month especially every
couple of months make sure you look back
and go okay it's been a while since I've
done any rotational stuff here I need to
do some more anti rotation work to
strengthen myself up there if you do all
that then you can put yourself together
a nice little program so what I like to
do here the famous saying that the
concepts are few but the methods are
many in the in the right hand or left
hand column or whatever it is you're
viewing this from I'm gonna go over
those basic concepts of strength again
kind of a summary and I'll add a couple
extra points and then on the the
right-hand side I'll give you a few
methods some of which you've probably
heard of but some maybe you have it
right now again the methods are infinite
I would encourage you to explore a bunch
of them just as long as you're executing
those methods while hitting these
concepts you should have no problem
getting stronger without adding too much
muscle mass so number one complex
movements like we just talked about
right all right so we generally don't
need to worry about doing forearm
isolating work or brachioradialis
specific work like that if the goal is
is as stated before 3 to 20 ish sets per
per exercise and then it really depends
right so if you're a beginner of course
heads more times 3 if you're advanced
maybe you can push it more towards 20
I'll give you an example for 2,000 I
think 7 national championships and
weightlifting one of the things I did
almost every day would be like 15 to 20
sets of 2 of a snatch and then 12 to 15
sets of 2 of a clean jerk and then 12 15
or so sets of 2 or 3 or 1 of a front
squat all right I was fairly advanced
competing at a reasonably high level
there and so I could do that but it just
depends on where your background is
right so these numbers can be really
good we want to be paying attention
though to the what's of what you can see
in yellow there all right so it's still
1 to 5 reps per set now I I did a pretty
famous podcast on Joe Rogan's platform a
couple of years or a year ago or so I
think and I talked about this and so if
you can go listen that if you want a
better explanation but one thing we want
to think about is is the difference
between something like 3 6 to 10 versus
10 sets of 3 so 3 sets of 10
is actually land you closer to what that
optimal hypertrophy zone is even though
the total amount of volume 30 reps is
the same between both groups ten sets of
three allows us to get what we call more
first reps or more high quality reps and
I'll get into that in just a second when
I talk about one of the methods but
that's really what we're talking about
okay so you so use that number of sets
as a sliding scale depending also on how
many days you're working out per week so
if you're working out the legs twice a
week versus four times a week well you
might be able to do less sets per day or
per muscle group or per exercise I mean
if you're working out more frequently
but if you're only doing legs once a
week you probably need to have more in
volume right which there are probably a
few reasons why you should ever do legs
once a week shame on you right
especially strength is the goal for a
bodybuilding or hypertrophy maybe get
away with it but basically everything
else we need frequency here like we said
80 to 100 percent ish plus of your
wonder up max has got to be heavy we've
already covered that point we want to
emphasize speed on all reps for the most
part I'll give you an exception to that
just a second but let's remember you're
not probably going to move very fast
because of force velocity curve tells us
when things get heavy you're a little
slower so because you're going heavy
it's gonna go slower find no problem but
there's also significant research that
says that suggests that the the interest
or the effort trying to go fast is maybe
more important than actually going fast
and so when the intent is to go fast
don't just do whatever is enough to move
the weight make sure you're really
trying to go as strong and hard as you
possibly can with all that being said we
want then maximal rest between each sets
so we're not trying to do this for a
condition piece if you're extremely out
of breath if you're sweating if you're
throwing up afterwards this is not
proper maximizing strength training you
want two to five minutes between sets
maybe seven eight depending on how heavy
it is how many you're doing let that the
you know be smart about that it doesn't
have to be magically in there but the
point is you want full maximal recovery
okay this also minimizes what's called
metabolic damage or metabolic fatigue
which is one of the ways you can induce
muscle hypertrophy
so if you stay nice and fresh no burning
tremendous fatigue happening that should
help you minimize the amount of muscle
hypertrophy so some of the methods one
of them push pulls carries presses
things we've already talked about drag a
big sled push things up a hill all very
very very good negatives knee Centrex
this is one thing I actually wish I
would have paid more attention to I went
like 10 or plus years without doing
anything like this but you've all done
this overload II Centrex right so if you
can bench a hundred pounds maybe you put
a hundred five pounds on and you just
lower it to your chest you have friends
lift it back up and then you go back to
those are called negatives or heavy
eccentric work very very good for
strength now be careful though be
careful on these for two reasons they're
pretty good at inducing hypertrophy and
- they're very damaging you're gonna get
really sore so don't use these things
too often you can still Pepperman know
once in a while and they're very very
very good for strength alongside that
isometric so I would encourage you to
check out Cal Dietz in his triphasic
program but the same thing here I regret
going probably 15 years without doing
really any eccentric work or isometric
work because I was too concerned about
you know moving slow I didn't want to
teach myself to be slow as a performance
athlete but I could have peppered him in
right I could have done it every once in
a while thrown in a couple of steps here
done a six-week block here and there
that wouldn't have really made me slow
over the course of the year the
isometrics and the east end tricks are
particularly good for movement control
movement quality for learning for for
motor control for technique as well as
for the connective tissue the ligaments
and joints and things like that
so that I think is a very very important
component to strength development weight
lifting movements of course so this
would be Olympic weight lifting snatch
planning jerks
variations push presses high poles
things like that all they are very very
good dynamic variable resistance is
another one some people also call this
compensatory acceleration you may have
heard of it just simply is like heavy
bands and chains I'm not talking about
those little Thera bands I'm talking
real thick heavy elastic bands you can
squat deadlift bench with them things
like that we've run some studies in our
laboratory specifically and a couple
have been done in some other places
across the country and these things are
quite effective as strength development
so they're very very good for force
production and I think Lois Simmons and
all the folks in the powerlifting
community have shown us 20 or 30 plus
years of of anecdotal evidence on this
and they're very good for strength
development you can maybe I'll make a
separate video for that if you'd like
let me know leave a comment or or send
me a note if you want a a five minute
fizz maybe on dynamic variable
resistance or accommodating resistance
sometimes called compensatory
acceleration all kind of different names
for it but that's a very good tactic I
would encourage people to put that stuff
in even if you're new so even for people
that are just getting into strength
training it still is gonna require some
very good control stabilization so it's
a good thing in general and then lastly
what are called cluster sets so this is
another thing that have probably got
twenty maybe thirty studies showing
these are very very effective I'm sure
most of you haven't heard of these
though so let me walk you through it
that means so imagine you're doing what
we call a traditional set three sets of
five repetitions how that would work is
you're gonna do one two three four five
reps in a row right then you take your
two two five minute break and then you
do one two three four or five reps in
row two-minute break one two three four
or five and that's your three sets of
five well with the cluster set it's the
exact same program design so you'd have
to change your program you can still do
three sets of five or whatever set range
are doing it doesn't matter if it's five
sets of three or whatever tens up to two
who cares right well the difference is
with the cluster you're going to take a
little mini break about ten to fifteen
to twenty seconds between each
repetition and then you'll still take
your two to five minute break in between
a set but there'll be a repetition break
so what it would look like is something
like this one rep sort of shake it all
out 1020 seconds one rep shake it all
out do your five reps take your two two
five minute break and then do that over
and over and over again it's funny
because in the weightlifting community
this is like what you do anyways right
so you do a snatch and then you drop it
down and it's like okay shake it out
reset your grip you know put the weights
back in line line it back up boom do
another rep and then you drop the bar
shake it all out line up boom do another
up and then I'll said you're like very
great like triple PR what
three reps it took you a minute to three
reps well by nature almost always weight
lifters tend to tend to do cluster sets
then but again like I said there is
strong scientific evidence to support
these things are as if not more
effective at strength development than
traditional sets and as I mentioned they
also reduce the metabolic disturbance or
the fatigue which can help mitigate
hypertrophy so a very very good
technique to utilize that being said
let's talk now about the physiology what
actually explains how I get stronger
once you understand this you don't have
to memorize that programming stuff
because it actually all explains itself
so let's have a little fun now and talk
about the physiology of getting stronger
without adding a ton of muscle mass all
right now there's four separate
categories I'm going to get into today
number one the nervous system is
probably what you've heard about if
you're a strength auditioning coach or a
student it's in any of your textbooks or
your certification exams but two three
four tend to be forgotten or simply not
known so let's dive into each one of
these one by one number one the nervous
system so we see significant adaptations
at the level of the central and
peripheral nervous system that allow us
to enhance force production again being
stronger without necessarily adding
muscle mass or being hypertrophy so
number one to start us off basic
physiology and anatomy tells us there's
what's called a motor unit and so you
can see an actual picture of it right
here you remember the basic anatomy of a
motor unit and so that's a a motor unit
is consisted of an alpha motor neuron er
all the muscle fibers that innervates
and so a nerve comes down or innervates
or activates a whole bunch of muscle
fibers that section together is what's a
motor unit now what we have is we have
what's called the all-or-none principle
and what this says is anytime that motor
unit is activated it contracts fully and
it activates every single muscle fiber
in its motor unit fully right so you
can't turn a nerve like 3/4 on you can't
turn on nerve on and tell it to activate
ten minutes
so fibers are only 12 of them it fires
at full strength and it activates all
the muscle fibers it's called the
all-or-none principle right so do use
the analogy of like a light switch okay
now imagine a motor unit won't functions
like a light flick when used move that
light switch 20% it's still totally dark
but whatever you break that seal boom it
goes 200% light right it's not like a
dimmer where you can slide go up 20% 25%
30% it is zero zero zero zero 100 100
100 100 100 100 0 all right it's all a
nun principle ok so what that means is
the only way that we can enhance force
production whether that's acutely or
chronically is to activate more motor
units to turn more nerves on so an
example here if I were to take this pen
and I wanted to scratch my eyeball oh my
god that's kind of scary
right well I wouldn't want to have every
single motor unit in my bicep being
focused on there because that I'd be
contracting at full speed I'm gonna
start off any movement by activating the
least and smallest amount of motor units
possible and only under one circumstance
do I activate more and that's when my
body is put on a situation in which the
requirements for force are higher so far
to add another thing to this list force
requirements go up now I activate more
motor units and for were to add a
10-pound weight to there more motor
units would go on and so what happens is
the vast majority of our motor units are
not being used as we add more force
production requirements I had more
activate more and more and more and more
this is again very common X phys if
you've had this class before right so
you can see there's little image you see
a lightning bolt it starts off in the
basic part of the neuron that activates
it goes down you should all remember
your basic anatomy from here right the
myelin sheath how it's jumping from node
to node going down the from the axon or
coming from the dendrites and goes all
the way down then it into a innervates
in each individual nerve so let's give
you a practical example imagine you're
like my friend Doug here and he's trying
to deadlift I think that was
20 kilos or something like that 500
pounds ish right as he starts to pull on
that bar bill he's initially only
activating a small percentage of his
motor neurons but as his body realizes
he needs more force production he's
gonna turn on more motor neurons and
more motor neurons and eventually if he
turns out enough neurons he'll have
enough force production to actually
start moving that barbell right and
that's how all strength training will
happens so one a the first adaptation
that we get is an increase in motor unit
activation right but only when more
forces required so the only way to get
stronger is specificity pick up heavy
things right you know what good this
from anything else so here you go here's
an example take a look at them right
here
boom perfect right did you notice that
pretty subtle but watch it one more time
see at the bottom here he starts to try
to lift the barbell and he realizes not
enough not enough not enough more
neurons more neurons eventually and then
you literally see that physiologic
phenomenon happen right in front of your
face
alright that's shout out to Doug Larson
barbell shrug go check him out
Douglas a Larson I think something like
that on histogram you can give him a
follow alright but that's a primary
example of this this this physiological
phenomenon of needing to activate more
motor units right well what this is is
it's it's an explanation or it's a
predecessor or a precursor rather for
what's called the size principle now the
size principle is founded by one of my
favorite Simon scientists of all time
Aldo and Henneman he's he's like your
favorite cramp alright like look at him
you know that guy has Werther's
Originals and in his front room right
fantastic guy like just the most warm
loving amazing guy well he put out a
series of publications in 1955 and 1956
and he basically said look the
susceptible throughout the nervous
system the susceptibility of neurons to
discharge as a function of their size
translation the smaller the neurons the
more likely are to discharge or fire
here's an example when the body sends
out a signal it sends it out to all the
neurons from the central nervous system
brain spinal cord right well how does it
know what your neurons to send it to
well it really doesn't care it just kind
of sends it to all of them well some of
your nerves the ones that tend to be
smaller are more susceptible to fire
when stimulated the bigger nerves need
more stimulus to actually fire so
smaller neurons are the ones that tend
to go first so it'll go back to our
pencil when I went to do this what am i
firing small or large neurons it's the
small ones right if I want to fire the
bigger neurons since they're less likely
to fire I have to give them tremendous
stimulus I have to really tell them I
really need your help right now please
come and give me help
right so as we go through the sequence
of pictures here and we start out the
bottom left-hand corner and we move our
we're in the middle into the top here's
what we see we see we have activated
small to bigger neurons all right now
what would happen if we did the opposite
what would happen if we started with big
to small neurons you see it wouldn't
work right because I wouldn't be able to
lift up this pencil without just doing
that every single time because I can't
turn down the dimmer switch they're all
on or they're all off so I have to go
from this small to big neurons this is
called the size principle again right I
go from small to big and so if you look
in this picture what we're seeing is
basically I've graphically depicted the
same thing so force production on the
bottom and recruitment threshold on this
side and you imagine those are each
individual muscle fibers or motor units
it doesn't particularly matter it's
gonna work the same well your muscles
don't actually just kind of turn
everything on it and they're not all the
same size and exact same shape so at low
levels of force production bottom left
we have low recruitment threshold that
was dug at the very bottom right didn't
think he needed a ton of force
production he started pulling he started
activating bigger higher threshold
neurons and force production went up so
he first started to get that barbell to
move then once he really activated the
super big super fast neurons or motor
units he finally was able to generate
enough force production to where he
could finally lift the barbell up in the
air right so this is really what we call
1c for going back to that original slide
so what can happen is in addition to
activating more motor neurons this sort
of a you to produce more force right in
addition to activating the bigger motor
neurons so really that's two adaptations
right just turning more neurons on and
activating bigger ones the third one
which is why we call it 1c is the rate
of motor unit activation now this is
going to get a bit trippy in somewhat
psychedelic here so don't tell my blood
so on me but like I said the nerves
aren't just like on they kind of
actually cycle back on and off on and
off on and off the neighboring ones and
so here's what it looks like you can see
the kind of animation like that so even
the low threshold ones would be cycling
on and off and as we go past them and go
into further even up to the lower
this is really what it would look like
right well one of the adaptations that
you're theoretically able to get with
through strength training is you can
increase the rate at which they're
starting and stopping so in the
animation all I've done is change the
cycling time on that animation you know
from once every half a second to ten
times that speed and watch what happens
that okay now I literally graphically
just or technologically just did that by
changing the frequency which that
animation happens it's making it more
fat rapid that's exactly what happens
with your motor unit activation you
increase the rate of activation you're
faster at doing that so because of that
you get that helicopter propeller effect
right where looks like you can track the
propeller because it's going so fast it
actually catches back up right well when
you do this you're able to generate more
total force production particularly in
terms of human movement right and then
finally one D is you're gonna increase
synchronization within and across muscle
groups so what that means is basically
this is a technique issue right it's a
neuromuscular technique so as you go to
do your deadlift or do your overhead
press or whatever it is you're doing
you've learned to turn on more and more
units you turn on bigger ones they they
cycle on faster but you also learn
exactly what order to turn which ones on
right so you start using more deltoids
here and then the deltoids kind of
Peters away so you can get more energy
to the tricep or whatever happens to be
so the motor units within each muscle
group just within the individual tricep
muscle or the deltoid muscle arm or
they're better off understanding when
they need to apply force and when they
don't when they need to save energy when
they really needed to give it and
they're also more likely to take it from
a muscle that doesn't need it and give
it to the specific ones to do so you
just get more neurologically
neuromuscular Li efficient your movement
and that's really what it comes down to
okay so that's nerve a number of motor
units activated size principle right
type 1 2 & 2 2 X's are slow fast and
super fast to its rate of motor you
activation a motor unit synchronization
the next big thing is muscle length so
we're still on a nerve
here and there's a reason okay this
one's particularly complicated it's been
taught often you've probably heard about
it but I almost guarantee you it's been
taught to you wrong so let's dive into
this muscle length issue while we're
here let's differentiate when I say
putting a muscle on stretch okay so I'm
not talking about stretching your muscle
I'm saying putting it like on an acute
stretch all right so when we say muscle
length here we're not talking about if I
get more flexibility in my hamstring I'm
talking about on this position versus
that position okay make that difference
all right maybe we'll do a separate
video on stretching or something if you
want there okay so the muscle the muscle
length determines force production all
right because of what's called the
length tension relationship now this is
a figure up here from the actual
original paper and it's really really
cool
so you remember from basic anatomy that
is called a sarcomere okay that's the
smallest functional unit of a muscle
cells so think individual muscle cell
don't think my quad think the individual
cell within it okay what this chart
beautifully shows you is the same force
curve actually that I showed you earlier
but what a depicts is force production
over length so at the bottom left-hand
corner there you see that at a small
sarcomere length there's no force
production and what happened that's
point five on the graph what happens as
we get to point four three and two as I
increase the length of the muscle force
production goes way up right until I
stretch too far and then force
production comes down so the length
tension relationship tells us at the
level of the sarcomere again just the
muscle fiber there's an optimal length
for force production too small and too
long or not good but somewhere in the
middle allows you to generate the most
force production you can see the actual
image there but this is why right if
you've had an atomy class if you haven't
go back and review on your own all right
but if you're one of my students I know
you've had this already next fin scoffs
but you remember the sliding filament
theory right so
the myosin and actin right the the
myosin reach up grab the actin contract
pulled together right we'll take a look
at the images here now it's kind of a
bit backwards here because remember five
is on the left and ones on the two but
in number one which is the far right if
you're too stretched out literally the
myosin can't reach the actin I can't
produce force if I can't connect the
myosin to the action because that has to
do my power stroke and pull everything
together right as I get shorter then so
this is two three and four here in the
middle on the bottom section myosin can
contract well with actin and cause good
force production but number five also
has no force production because the
myosin actin are already up next to each
other as high as they can get so I can't
smash them together any further
so here myosin actin too close together
here a good distance good powerful power
stroke here too long can't reach each
other we've got problems right well this
is a length tension relationship now
remember this is length tension it's
specifically and only refers to the
sarcomere this is actually these
experiments were originally done and I
think frog muscle they isolated the Frog
muscle put on a pea tradition and found
this stuff out but that's not how whole
muscle contracts and so yes
length tension is important but that's
not exactly how whole muscle function
works so if we look in anatomical
position right you all know this from
basic anatomy every muscle in the
anatomical position is that what we call
resting length all right so LT length
tense relationship is optimized for
every angle at the muscle resting length
aka an Tomica position so if I'm
standing here like this all of those
muscles for the most part of my body are
at the equal distance in the middle
they're not too smashed together they're
not too stretched apart but length
tension ship doesn't account for a nerve
it doesn't account for connective tissue
or biomechanics and so that in and of
itself doesn't tell me everything I need
to know about muscle contraction and
let's be real all of us here because we
care about what makes the barbell or the
dumbbell or the wheel or whatever
they're in the car whatever we're
pushing move right so we can't
interpret length tension relationship
what commonly happens here is people
read they learn a little bit about
length tense relationship they think
they're for muscle contraction is
optimal in the middle therefore I'm
gonna do my work like this never too
small never too high no full range of
motion because this is where the most
force production happens well that's a
gross misunderstanding what the length
tension relationship can actually tell
us because it doesn't account for nerve
connective or biomechanics so let me
show you what that means
here's another image okay so muscle
doesn't move bone muscle goes into
connective tissue fashion into a tendon
tendon connects into bone okay
so look at the color coding there and
blue skeletal muscle and red tendon and
fashion ok so here's what really happens
whole muscle force production is that
length 10th - relationship combined with
those elastic components attend in the
fashio right if you take whatever muscle
did combine that with however while you
transferred that force through the
connective tissue to the bone that will
determine whole muscle force production
because that determines what actually
move the bone right which is bone then
moves implement so let's combine all
these things going back to this original
length tension relationship just like I
described this is that same white black
and white figure thing I just kind of
made an updated version here's what it
basically says at resting length in the
middle we have our contractile tension
now when I say contractile tension think
muscle contraction length tension
relationship and that's that inverted
you right boom this is the same slide
from a couple of slides ago that was in
black and white okay do small coatrack
actin myosin together too far apart
can't reach optimal strength force
production in the middle but at resting
length since the elastic part is like a
rubber band okay at rest there's not any
tension in a rubber band okay unlike
muscle at rest there's already a
tremendous amount of tension there it's
possible right and as I stretch a rubber
band is there an optimal length pinch
relationship with a rubber band No
the more you pull the rubber band the
more force production goes into it until
it snaps right and so that actually
looks just like that you keep applying
stretch to a tendon it'll continue to
increase its force production right just
do your bicep pull it back like that let
it go it's gonna fly back right the
tendon wants to go back to resting
length everything wants to go back to
resting length so when we do a whole
body contraction whatever it's going to
be like a like a punch right and we're
going through here well I'm over
stretched here I'm gonna pour length
tension relationship but every ounce of
stretch I get here increases the elastic
tension right as I start contracting I
lose elastic tension but as I get more -
resting length I gain resting length all
right so what I can do to maximize total
muscle force production is combine my
elastic with my contractile tension I
can't just go from here because I'm not
gonna be getting any extra advantage
from a rubber band right anyone that
knows this would punch if the person
wasn't moving by putting a muscle on the
biggest stretch possible I would turn my
hips first because that actually
disassociates the joints which is
another way of saying I put this thing
on stretch by just moving the lower half
and keeping this in the same spot and
now I get the most force production so
total overall tension looks like that
right so with almost any human movement
from the muscles perspective now we have
a counter from biomechanics yet our
mechanical advantage they go on but from
the muscles perspective the take-home
message I'm saying here is more stretch
more force production right now there's
cause to that that's how we pull a
hamstring and for over-striding right
and our and our leg Brian Mackenzie
Stott us that right we're over striding
in our foots flailing way back since we
are getting so much more force
production boom we can pull the
hamstring but this is really what it's
about
you want to maximize forage production
you want to combine the contractile with
the elastic elements and yes when you
move past resting
I start to lose contractile tension I
gain more elastic tension that I lose
and contract out so my net force
production keeps going up immense it
like this you are running to do a sprint
and a couple of steps into it I get
behind you and push you a little bit
extra well you're going so much faster
by the time you get back to resting
length because you use elastic tension
to get started you're going so much
faster I can generate more total force
or speed or power whatever I'm trying to
produce because I use that elastic
tension okay and so because this is
going to be summarized in what I call
one of my major laws have strength
addition which is to say that we should
generally train all of our joints
through all of our ranges of motion
because of this right now there's a
bunch of other reasons to do that and I
said generally not always but for the
most part we want to train all of our
joints through all of our range of
motions for three primary reasons number
one we want to maintain the lane to
motion right you don't use it you're
eventually going to lose it and the
easiest way to become flexible and
mobile is to never lose it in the first
place right so the more we train through
big ranges of motion the more we're
likely to keep those ranges of motion
right I'm never asking you to do a range
of motion that puts you in a bad
position right so I don't want a joint
in a bad position
this would specifically be things like
the lumbar spine potentially the knee
but for the most part go through your
Anatomy and understand the range of the
motion that occur in each joint and then
think am i training am I going through
those full range of motion if you are
it's good if the joint is supposed to go
there then it's good the reason why I
like a valgus collapse is bad for our
knees because the knee is supposed to do
flex I extend it's not supposed to go
that way so that way to have movements
bad but the full flexion extension is
great for the knee it's full range of
motion number two it helped you activate
all or most musculature now I'll cover
that in a separate video but that's an
important point we need to be able to
activate all the musculature joints that
cross multiple joints aren't fully
activated when one of those joints is
slack okay
so it's a bit wordy but trust me on that
one so for
motion helps us activate almost goodra
and in the last one which is what we
just covered we spent extensive time on
all right so more stretch is more force
why because the elastic response is
passive and subconscious in other words
if you take your finger and you were to
put it on a table and snap it like that
well you're using the elasticity in that
tendon in the muscle in the finger right
there right it's passive it's not
burning ATP there's no bioenergetics
involved it's just returning back to
normal it's a rubber band snapping okay
and it's subconscious right think of the
Achilles when you're running if you land
heel first or if you land on your foot
the elastic the Achilles tendon will
give you a certain amount of course
production and balance and that saves
you a ton of energy stress shorting
cycle is another one right so the
stretch shortening cycle says anytime
I've got my proprioception going on you
need timing muscle is stretched it wants
to respond by contracting right so if
I'm in pre stretch a muscle more it
never it inherently just wants to
contract that is active it does take ATP
but it's also subconscious so I can get
more force production by just putting a
muscle on stretch right this is why I
would dip quickly before I would do it
Jone things like that and then see like
we said the contractile tension it's
active right I'm active trying to
contract my muscle that's also mat of
control and it's conscious right so if
we combine all three those levels a b
and c we're going to get the most force
production possible all right so that's
why we want to train all of our range of
motion so that's it from the nerve now
let's transition and it's much shorter
here two points two three and four but
like I said this is the part you
probably have not heard before so
turning our attention to the more
important or interesting stuff just
getting on a muscle guys so I always
think that's those better let's talk
about muscles so there are a host of
adaptations that occur in muscle that
allow you to be stronger without getting
bigger so then I don't mean muscle I per
trophy all right people think that it's
either nervous system and that explains
all the reasons why you get stronger not
bigger but let's not forget the
contribution that can happen
you probably need to go back and do
yourself a thorough review of muscle
structure and micro anatomy but I'm not
gonna do that here I will fully expect
that you understand the neuromuscular
Junction how that works and also you
should be able to review and walk
yourself say in an open essay form at
the top of your head how the entire
action potential happens how calcium is
released and how things are transmitters
cross a neuromuscular Junction they open
those sodium ligand gated open channels
and things like that what I see the
coaling is what it does how to recycle
what Achilles alkaline esterase does all
that stuff should be important you
should also be able to continue from
there and explain or off the top of your
head how calcium is released some
sarcoplasmic reticulum
well the accidental travels down the T
tubules and in that whole sliding
filament theory thing right so troponin
tropomyosin causing conformational
changes how the powerstroke Capon is a
role of ATPase and all that stuff and
then how its reset now what happens I
don't think memorizing the voltage and
all that stuff is particularly important
but just least the functionality what
actually occurs here is very important
while we're at it I think it would made
do those people a bit of help here to
take a look at the Z lines and then
discs and all that Micro Anatomy
structure wearing lines and troponin and
tropomyosin like I said before but even
what's the thick or thin filaments
what's in what's Titan what's nebula n--
z disk if you take any certification in
this field strength auditioning
particularly like the CSCS from the NSCA
they're gonna ask you a lot of questions
about that so I'm not gonna waste your
time going without here I'm just gonna
have to assume you know some of this
knowledge but this is all good stuff
that you tend to get asked on a lot of
these Commons certifications alright
well and then new ADP hydrolysis and all
that stuff okay but more importantly
let's take a look at the big picture
well regardless of what you're trying to
do you have to generate ATP that's our
only energy currency in all of biology
all of living cells right whether using
phosphocreatine carbohydrate fat or
protein I've covered this in other
videos right you can go back and take a
look at
we're all trying to get to a teepee once
you get to eighty be a teepee you want
to split it into ATP inorganic phosphate
and that releases heat a whole bunch of
energy or a whole bunch a heat sorry and
a little bit of energy then we use that
energy to power things like muscle
contraction performance okay well here's
what could happen that you can get
tremendous increases in efficiency at
that muscle energy level for example you
can store a lot more creatine phosphate
that allows you to produce more force
more frequently and virtually anything
that I discovered and all of it adapts
to strength training right so for
example the calcium in the sarcoplasmic
reticulum it gets released sooner when
your more strength right and it's more
sensitive the affinity to calcium on the
troponin and tropomyosin complex on the
myosin head it's higher you increase the
amount of acetylcholine you have you
increase the amount of receptors you
have at the cell t tubules get larger
every single part of that equation has
been shown at some level to increase or
whatever the change is to make this
system more efficient with strength
training this is why I'm not gonna walk
you through all of those things that
would be another like three hours of
video right but basically everything in
that chain if you were to be ever be
asked a question about how would the
from the cellular energy perspective
increased force production as long as
you walk through any stuff basically
pick it and say it changes it increases
with chronic strength training there's
at least some mild took depending on
some of the stuff very strong evidence
to show that that actually is the case
and so all of those changes again
allowed that muscle cell to come to
produce and contract with more force it
doesn't necessarily make it any bigger
it doesn't have to just be large and
have a greater cross-sectional area so
number two be then fiber type and this
is also synonymous with contraction
velocity right there's a reason we call
it a fast twitch cuz it twitches ready
for it ready for it faster
alright but here you go this is what our
lab does if this is the first video
you've seen from me you're gonna get to
know it but if not this is the primary
thing I emphasize so what you're seeing
actually right there and the far corner
is a
muscle sample from the muscle biopsy you
can see in the bottom all those
individual muscle cells that are just
sort of hanging out right so this is
what we do is we take muscle samples
from people we pull out cells one at a
time and then we can analyze this thing
for their fiber type fast slow twitch
things like that well this is actually
an image it's kind of dark with dark on
purpose you see a little purple line in
the corner vertical line that's actually
our laser of scanning confocal
microscope with my colleague Jimmy
Bagley and that's actually firing
through one individual muscle cell on a
glass plate or worth taking some really
high hide that very zoomed in 3d images
of a muscle fiber but regardless in
terms of fiber type depending on where
you've been taught or where you've read
you may have heard that we can convert
fast to slow twitch or slow to fast or
neither or both or something weird well
I'm here to tell you as sorry for the
arrogance but one of the world's
foremost leaders in muscle fiber type
transitions of exercise it's very clear
it happens in all directions and it's
very specific to the type of attitude
and exercise you do it goes back to said
right it basically looks like this right
this is my friend Mike Bledsoe and their
barbell shrug girth look at them lining
up there but here's an example if you
take a person's quadricep typically
they're about 50% fast which and
pick.you percent slopes which if you
look at another muscle saying the soleus
which is the the calf muscle
anti-gravity postural muscle it's like
80% slow-twitch maybe even higher
alright so every individual muscle has a
different fiber type composition and
what we call in the muscle biology is
structure and function follow each other
so for example if you look like at the
quad it's 50% fast 50% slow that
generally means it helps with slow
twitch type of things which are standing
up all day walking and but it can also
help with high power high force things
like jumping the soli this is pretty
much there to keep you vertical all day
keep you walking all day and it's not
really needed for how our helpful from
force production its little neighbor
though the gastroc that other big calf
muscle is almost the inverse it's almost
entirely slow twitch so the gastroc is
there for sprinting and jumping but the
soleus is there to keep you vertical and
erect all day
well we also see tremendous
person-to-person differences so we have
had people in my laboratory that are 90%
slow-twitch and their quad in that exact
same muscle group and i'm when i'm by
quad i mean specifically vastus
lateralis to be almost on the outside
one I have biopsy other people that are
90 percent fast which and so really you
can run the gamut in the exact same
muscle whether it's you or Hercules
right there may be a different
composition of these faster they're slow
Church fibers and so this is an example
this is from again Jimi Bagley's work I
published this in 2012 so really what we
see is this continuum okay so on one
hand you have the type ones which are
the very slow twitch fibers you can see
them in image there they're very slow
but they have a tremendous endurance on
the other and a spectrum you see type 2
X which are extremely fast and are very
glycolytic which means they use
carbohydrates very well for energy but
they fatigue very quickly and then we
have water we would call hybrid fibers
that are in the middle so see that slow
fast and that fast ultra fast those are
single individual muscle cells that Co
express either in this case that's half
fast half slower half as fast have ultra
fast now I'm not gonna get any more
details here I have a like a two and a
half hour video on this topic up you can
go check other videos I have a
five-minute version of the fiber types
up as well so you can go check that
stuff out there but effectively what
you're looking at is this when you do
steady-state endurance type of work you
increase the amount of slow twitch
fibers you how again clearly Shawn
depending on what you do you may
decrease or not change the amount of
slow twitch you have if you do something
moral again this is mike blood so this
is fantastic but i don't think he even
knows i have this photo
you know you think it's bad doing bicep
curls in the squat rack try doing bicep
curls in there and the glute-ham raise
machine come on man but if you know mike
or you've heard of him go tag him tell
him tell him about this he's gonna be so
confused and not i what's going on but
again i don't think even those i have
this picture point is if you do like the
classic hyper true for you three sets of
ten things like that you will see an
increase in slow twitch and faster
fibers with a specific decrease
and those hybrid fibers more plyometric
true speed stuff certainly seen increase
in fast twitch with probably no increase
in slow twitch but what we don't know a
tremendous amount about is anything else
I don't know a lot about intervals I
don't know a lot about circuits we don't
know a lot about strength training or
different types of strength training or
powerlifting training versus whether
than training we just simply don't know
we haven't done a lot of interventions I
don't mean we've just the field hasn't
done interventions there so at the
surface level this is basically what
we're looking about so if you're to put
this together
if you likely did some pure strength
training like I talked about in the
beginning with the prescription you
would almost surely see an increasing
amount of fast twitch fibers you have if
you do that you should be able to
generate a lot more force not
necessarily being any bigger now
typically the fast twitch fibers are
often times bigger than the slow twitch
but not necessarily just in the hair
just changing it's tight doesn't itself
increase its size and I'll give you a
good example what we can do in our lab
is we can take these individual fibers
and put them up into a little petri dish
time to the end of a force transducer
and we can measure its individual force
production outside of the body so what
we typically see is you can see this the
MHC ones versus the two ways so the ones
are or the two ways are typically much
more powerful that's a single fiber
level than the ones fast waste versus
slow touch no surprise the fast which
has more power than the slow touch but
what most people don't understand is
that contractility can increase in both
fiber types post chronic strength Tran
so take a look at the type ones even the
ones that didn't convert to 2a
the ones that stay the type one can get
more powerful independent of size they
can simply produce more force through
the mechanisms I talked about in point a
right all those micro Anatomy things
happen that can improve efficiency and
power production independent of size the
two ways as well so if we look at muscle
combined we have multiple scenarios here
the energy stuff the fiber type can
transition or we can simply produce more
force or power all without necessarily
just getting bigger
so one of my other important laws that
we'll talk about and my classes a lot is
muscle is extremely plastic virtually
every single thing we know how it
functions changes with training so that
brings out a thing that people here
commonly which is what we call our early
versus late strength out of patience
this is a fancy way of saying how is it
when you take someone and they've only
been lifting for say two or three weeks
or maybe even a week and all of a sudden
they're stronger well it's not because I
portray fear of course what is it then
what's that you say ah everyone wants to
say well the answer is because of
neurological and while that is true as I
just outlined don't give all of the
benefit to the nerve system there's a
lot of muscular adaptations that happen
that allow you to also be stronger very
quickly not necessarily being any bigger
so typically you know those first four
to ten or twelve weeks or whatever you
want to call it those adaptations that
allow you to be stronger now before
you've actually put on any additional
muscle mass are mainly neurological we
talked about a number of them right
frequency of firing you also have things
like increased relaxation of antagonists
muscle groups so what you may not
realize is during a bicep curl your
tricep the antagonist actually fires one
of the adaptations you learn quickly is
to relax your tricep right because if
you fired your bicep at the same time
you fired your tricep you wouldn't move
so am i simply relaxing your tricep that
allows you to move the bicep more
effectively any change in that
neuromuscular Junction sign right so in
those micro anatomy the synaptic
vesicles increasing acetylcholine all
that stuff or decreases in gto Golgi
tendon organ resistance so it's very
similar to what I was saying earlier the
GTOs measure attention and when they
measure and they realize tension is
occurring they respond by turning the
muscle contraction off and so that can
happen as well but like I said then on
all neurological so don't forget about
those changes in calcium kinetics and
muscular junctions stuff fiber type or
contractility that can produce more
force our last couple of points here
three and four very quick just be
because we've already exhausted the
topic connective tissue is sort of the
Forgotten child here so we can clearly
have increases and decreases in
efficiency of of force transfer through
the connective tissue we just don't have
much research and we don't understand
how well this can be done with an
intervention like strength training
same thing with mechanical advantage all
right so the last final point here I'm
ignoring biomechanics for basically all
of this right so you can look into that
field but if you change mechanical
advantage panache and angle all this
stuff matters and all these things
panache and angle specifically does
change with with training and this is
angle at which your muscle lands into
the nerve and the muscle I'm sorry the
muscle the angle at which your muscle
lands in a bone okay so if you change
that angle one way it favors range of
motion and speed if it goes the opposite
direction of favors force production
this can influence general force
production as well without necessarily
being any bigger limb length changes
changes in technique that alter
mechanical advantage versus disadvantage
things like that so you can go then and
learn about your class one two and three
levers if you take a certification exam
you need to know it not in my classes
ever but things like this are important
and relevant to the conversation so that
being said hopefully you've learned more
in this short short short video about
how you can get stronger without any
adding any additional amounts so once
again I appreciate you can check more
videos like this out for me and II
Galpin my website any Galpin comm and if
you feel like you've learned and earned
some value here I would certainly
appreciate a contribution of a buck or
two to my patreon account that's patreon
PA Treo and comm /a knee Galpin you can
also check this out on all of my various
social media at my Instagram account at
dr. Andy Galpin and such but for now
thank you for your time and let's make
the world a better place
Cheers
you